<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    DO NOT ALTER OR REMOVE COPYRIGHT NOTICES OR THIS HEADER.

    Copyright (c) 2010-2017 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

    The contents of this file are subject to the terms of either the GNU
    General Public License Version 2 only ("GPL") or the Common Development
    and Distribution License("CDDL") (collectively, the "License").  You
    may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  You can
    obtain a copy of the License at
    https://oss.oracle.com/licenses/CDDL+GPL-1.1
    or LICENSE.txt.  See the License for the specific
    language governing permissions and limitations under the License.

    When distributing the software, include this License Header Notice in each
    file and include the License file at LICENSE.txt.

    GPL Classpath Exception:
    Oracle designates this particular file as subject to the "Classpath"
    exception as provided by Oracle in the GPL Version 2 section of the License
    file that accompanied this code.

    Modifications:
    If applicable, add the following below the License Header, with the fields
    enclosed by brackets [] replaced by your own identifying information:
    "Portions Copyright [year] [name of copyright owner]"

    Contributor(s):
    If you wish your version of this file to be governed by only the CDDL or
    only the GPL Version 2, indicate your decision by adding "[Contributor]
    elects to include this software in this distribution under the [CDDL or GPL
    Version 2] license."  If you don't indicate a single choice of license, a
    recipient has the option to distribute your version of this file under
    either the CDDL, the GPL Version 2 or to extend the choice of license to
    its licensees as provided above.  However, if you add GPL Version 2 code
    and therefore, elected the GPL Version 2 license, then the option applies
    only if the new code is made subject to such option by the copyright
    holder.

-->

<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "metro.ent">
%ents;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="ahiaj" xml:lang="en"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Introduction to Metro</title>

    <section xml:id="ahiae">
        <title>Required Software</title>

        <para>To use this guide, download and install the following
        software:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><link
                xlink:href="http://download.oracle.com/javase/">Oracle JavaSE
                Runtime or Development Kit</link></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Container (note: Metro can be run on any Servlet
                container) <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><link
                            xlink:href="http://glassfish.java.net/public/downloadsindex.html">GlassFish
                            Server</link></para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                            <para><link
                            xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat
                            Servlet Container</link></para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://metro.java.net/">Metro</link>
                binary. See the particular release page for instructions about
                downloading and installing Metro in a servlet
                container.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><link
                xlink:href="http://netbeans.org/downloads/index.html">NetBeans
                IDE</link> (Java version)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ahiak">
        <title>What is WSIT?</title>

        <para>For three years (and continuing) Sun has worked closely with
        Microsoft to ensure interoperability of web services enterprise
        technologies such as security , reliable messaging, and atomic
        transactions. That portion of Metro is known as WSIT (Web Service
        Interoperability Technologies). Metro's WSIT subsystem is an
        implementation of a number of open web services specifications to
        support enterprise features. In addition to security, reliable
        messaging, and atomic transactions, Metro includes a bootstrapping and
        configuration technology. <xref linkend="ahial"
        xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows the underlying services that were
        implemented for each technology.</para>

        <figure xml:id="ahial">
            <title>Metro's WSIT Web Services Features</title>

            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                               fileref="figures/WSITwebServicesFeatures.png"
                               scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>

                <textobject>
                    <simpara>Diagram showing Metro's WSIT web services
                    features: Core XML, Core Web Services, Bootstrapping,
                    Security, and Reliability</simpara>
                </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Starting with the core XML support currently built into the Java
        platform, Metro uses or extends existing features and adds new support
        for interoperable web services. See the following sections for an
        overview of each feature:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiam" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiao" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiap" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiaq" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section xml:id="ahiam">
            <title>Bootstrapping and Configuration</title>

            <para>Bootstrapping and configuration consists of using a URL to
            access a web service, retrieving its WSDL file, and using the WSDL
            file to create a web service client that can access and consume a
            web service. The process consists of the following steps, which
            are shown in <xref linkend="ahian"
            xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahian">
                <title>Bootstrapping and Configuration</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/bootstrappingConfiguration.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram showing bootstrapping and
                        configuration</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Client acquires the URL for a web service that it
                    wants to access and consume. How you acquire the URL is
                    outside the scope of this tutorial. For example, you might
                    look up the URL in a Web Services registry.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>The client uses the URL and the
                    <code>wsimport</code> tool to send a WS-MetadataExchange
                    Request to access the web service and retrieve the WSDL
                    file. The WSDL file contains a description of the web
                    service endpoint, including WS-Policy assertions that
                    describe the security, reliability, transactional, etc.,
                    capabilities and requirements of the service. The
                    description describes the requirements that must be
                    satisfied to access and consume the web service.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>The client uses the WSDL file to create the web
                    service client.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>The web service client accesses and consumes the web
                    service.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para><xref linkend="bootstrap_config" xrefstyle="select:title" />
            explains how to bootstrap and configure a web service client and a
            web service endpoint that use the Metro's WSIT
            technologies.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiao">
            <title>Message Optimization Technology</title>

            <para>A primary function of web services applications is to share
            data among applications over the Internet. The data shared can
            vary in format and include large binary payloads, such as
            documents, images, music files, and so on. When large binary
            objects are encoded into XML format for inclusion in SOAP
            messages, even larger files are produced. When a web service
            processes and transmits these large files over the network, the
            performance of the web service application and the network are
            negatively affected. In the worst case scenario the effects are as
            follows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The performance of the web service application
                    degrades to a point that it is no longer useful.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>The network gets bogged down with more traffic than
                    the allotted bandwidth can handle.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>One way to deal with this problem is to encode the binary
            objects so as to optimize both the SOAP application processing
            time and the bandwidth required to transmit the SOAP message over
            the network. In short, XML needs to be optimized for web services.
            This is the exactly what the Message Optimization technology does.
            It ensures that web services messages are transmitted over the
            Internet in the most efficient manner.</para>

            <para>Sun recommends that you use message optimization if your web
            service client or web service endpoint will be required to process
            binary encoded XML documents larger than 1KB.</para>

            <para>For instructions on how to use the Message Optimization
            technology, see <xref linkend="ahibx"
            xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiap">
            <title>Reliable Messaging Technology</title>

            <para>Reliable Messaging is a Quality of Service (QoS) technology
            for building more reliable web services. Reliability (in terms of
            what is provided by WS-ReliableMessaging) is measured by a
            system's ability to deliver messages from point A to point B. The
            primary purpose of Reliable Messaging is to ensure the delivery of
            application messages to web service endpoints.</para>

            <para>The reliable messaging technology ensures that messages in a
            given message sequence are delivered at least once and not more
            than once and optionally in the correct order. When messages in a
            given sequence are lost in transit or delivered out of order, this
            technology enables systems to recover from such failures. If a
            message is lost in transit, the sending system retransmits the
            message until its receipt is acknowledged by the receiving system.
            If messages are received out of order, the receiving system may
            re-order the messages into the correct order.</para>

            <para>You should consider using reliable messaging if the web
            service is experiencing the following types of problems:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Communication failures are occurring that result in
                    the network being unavailable or connections being
                    dropped</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Application messages are being lost in
                    transit</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Application messages are arriving at their
                    destination out of order and ordered delivery is a
                    requirement</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>To help decide whether or not to use reliable messaging,
            weigh the following advantages and disadvantages:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enabling reliable messaging ensures that messages
                    are delivered exactly once from the source to the
                    destination and, if the ordered-delivery option is
                    enabled, ensures that messages are delivered in
                    order.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Enabling reliable messaging uses more memory
                    (especially if the ordered delivery option is enabled)
                    since messages must be stored (even after they are sent)
                    until receipt is acknowledged.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Non-reliable messaging clients cannot interoperate
                    with web services that have reliable messaging
                    enabled.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>For instructions on how to use the Reliable Messaging
            technology, see <xref linkend="using_rm"
            xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiaq">
            <title>Security Technology</title>

            <para>Until now, web services have relied on transport-based
            security such as SSL to provide point-to-point security. Metro
            implements WS-Security so as to provide interoperable message
            content integrity and confidentiality, even when messages pass
            through intermediary nodes before reaching their destination
            endpoint. WS-Security as provided by Metro is in addition to
            existing transport-level security, which may still be used.</para>

            <para>Metro also enhances security by implementing WS-Secure
            Conversation, which enables a consumer and provider to establish a
            shared security context when a multiple-message-exchange sequence
            is first initiated. Subsequent messages use derived session keys
            that increase the overall security while reducing the security
            processing overhead for each message.</para>

            <para>Further, Metro implements two additional features to improve
            security in web services:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Trust</emphasis>: Enables web
                    service applications to use SOAP messages to request
                    security tokens that can then be used to establish trusted
                    communications between a client and a web service.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Security Policy</emphasis>:
                    Enables web services to use security assertions to clearly
                    represent security preferences and requirements for web
                    service endpoints.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Metro implements these features in such a way as to ensure
            that web service binding security requirements, as defined in the
            WSDL file, can interoperate with and be consumed by Metro and WCF
            endpoints.</para>

            <para>For instructions on how to use the WS-Security technology,
            see <xref linkend="ahici" xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ahiar">
        <title>How Metro Relates to .NET Windows Communication Foundation
        (WCF)</title>

        <para>Web services interoperability is an initiative of Sun and
        Microsoft. We test and deliver products to market that interoperate
        across different platforms.</para>

        <para>Metro is the product of Sun's web services interoperability
        initiative. Windows Communication Foundation (WCF) in .NET is
        Microsoft's unified programming model for building connected systems.
        WCF, which is available as part of the .NET Framework 3.x product,
        includes application programming interfaces (APIs) for building
        secure, reliable, transacted web services that interoperate with
        non-Microsoft platforms.</para>

        <para>Sun Microsystems and Microsoft jointly test Metro against WCF to
        ensure that Sun web service clients (consumers) and web services
        (producers) do in fact interoperate with WCF web services applications
        and vice versa. This testing ensures that the following
        interoperability goals are realized:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Metro web services clients can access and consume WCF
                web services.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>WCF web services clients can access and consume Metro
                web services.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Sun provides Metro on the Java platform and Microsoft provides
        WCF on the .NET 3.0 and .NET 3.5 platforms. The sections that follow
        describe the web services specifications implemented by Sun
        Microsystems in Web Services Interoperability Technologies (WSIT) and
        provide high-level descriptions of how each WSIT technology
        works.</para>

        <note>
            <para>Because Metro-based clients and services are interoperable,
            you can gain the benefits of Metro without using WCF.</para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ahias">
        <title>Metro Specifications</title>

        <para>The specifications for bootstrapping and configuration, message
        optimization, reliable messaging, and security technologies are
        discussed in the following sections:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiat" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiav" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiax" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para><xref linkend="ahiaz" xrefstyle="select:title" /></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Metro implements the following WS-* specifications.</para>

        <table frame="all" xml:id="gfrxa">
            <title>Metro Specification Versions</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Technology</entry>

                        <entry>Metro Version</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Bootstrapping</entry>

                        <entry>since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2004/09/mex/WS-MetadataExchange.pdf">WS-MetadataExchange
                        v1.1</link> <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Policy (W3C standards)</entry>

                        <entry>since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Submission/WS-Policy/">WS-Policy
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/Submission/WS-PolicyAttachment/">WS-PolicyAttachment
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/PR-ws-policy-20070706/">WS-Policy
                        v1.5</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/PR-ws-policy-attach-20070706/">WS-PolicyAttachment
                        v1.5</link> <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Reliable Messaging (OASIS standards)</entry>

                        <entry>since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/02/rm/ws-reliablemessaging.pdf">WS-ReliableMessaging
                        v1.0</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/02/rm/WS-RMPolicy.pdf">WS-ReliableMessaging
                        Policy v1.0</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/documents.php?wg_abbrev=ws-rx">WS-ReliableMessaging
                        v1.1</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 :
                        WS-ReliableMessaging Policy v1.1<?linebreak ?> since
                        v2.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-rx/wsrm/v1.2/wsrm.html">WS-ReliableMessaging
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v2.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-rx/wsrmp/v1.2/wsrmp.html">WS-ReliableMessaging
                        Policy v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v2.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-rx/wsmc/v1.1/wsmc.html">WS-MakeConnection
                        v1.1</link> <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Atomic Transactions (OASIS standards)</entry>

                        <entry>since v2.1 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-tx/wstx-wsat-1.2-spec-os.pdf">WS-AtomicTransaction
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v2.1 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-tx/wstx-wscoor-1.2-spec-os.pdf">WS-Coordination
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Security (OASIS standards)</entry>

                        <entry>since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/wss/2004/01/oasis-200401-wss-soap-message-security-1.0.pdf">WS-Security
                        v1.0</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/16790/wss-v1.1-spec-os-SOAPMessageSecurity.pdf">WS-Security
                        v1.1</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/07/securitypolicy/ws-securitypolicy.pdf">WS-SecurityPolicy
                        v1.1</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-securitypolicy/200702/ws-securitypolicy-1.2-spec-cs.html">WS-SecurityPolicy
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/02/trust/WS-Trust.pdf">WS-Trust
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-trust/200512/ws-trust-1.3-os.html">WS-Trust
                        v1.3</link> <?linebreak ?> since v2.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-trust/v1.4/os/ws-trust-1.4-spec-os.html">WS-Trust
                        v1.4</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://specs.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/02/sc/WS-SecureConversation.pdf">WS-SecureConversation
                        v1.2</link> <?linebreak ?> since v1.3 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-secureconversation/200512/ws-secureconversation-1.3-os.html">WS-SecureConversation
                        v1.3</link> <?linebreak ?> since v2.0 : <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-sx/ws-secureconversation/v1.4/os/ws-secureconversation-1.4-spec-os.html">WS-SecureConversation
                        v1.4</link> <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Security Profiles (OASIS standards)</entry>

                        <entry>since v1.3 All 1.0 and 1.1 profiles listed
                        <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wss">here</link>
                        except <link
                        xlink:href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/wss/oasis-wss-rel-token-profile-1.0.pdf">Web
                        Services Security REL Token Profile V1.0</link>
                        <?linebreak ?></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Metro 1.3 + and WCF in .NET 3.5 implement the same
        specifications.</para>

        <para>Metro 1.0 - 1.2 and WCF in .NET 3.0 implement the same
        specifications.</para>

        <section xml:id="ahiat">
            <title>Bootstrapping and Configuration Specifications</title>

            <para>Bootstrapping and configuring involves a client getting a
            web service URL (perhaps from a service registry) and obtaining
            the information needed to build a web services client that is
            capable of accessing and consuming a web service over the
            Internet. This information is usually obtained from a WSDL file.
            <xref linkend="ahiau" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows the
            specifications that were implemented to support bootstrapping and
            configuration.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahiau">
                <title>Bootstrapping and Configuration Specifications</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/BootstrappingConfigStandards.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of bootstrapping and configuration
                        specifications</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In addition to the Core XML specifications, bootstrapping
            and configuration was implemented using the following
            specifications:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>WSDL</emphasis>: WSDL is a standardized
                    XML format for describing network services. The
                    description includes the name of the service, the location
                    of the service, and ways to communicate with the service,
                    that is, what transport to use. WSDL descriptions can be
                    stored in service registries, published on the Internet,
                    or both.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Policy</emphasis>: This
                    specification provides a flexible and extensible grammar
                    for expressing the capabilities, requirements, and general
                    characteristics of a web service. It provides the
                    mechanisms needed to enable web services applications to
                    specify policy information in a standardized way. However,
                    this specification does not provide a protocol that
                    constitutes a negotiation or message exchange solution for
                    web Services. Rather, it specifies a building block that
                    is used in conjunction with the WS-Metadata Exchange
                    protocol. When applied in the web services model, policy
                    is used to convey conditions on interactions between two
                    web service endpoints. Typically, the provider of a web
                    service exposes a policy to convey conditions under which
                    it provides the service. A requester might use the policy
                    to decide whether or not to use the service.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Metadata Exchange</emphasis>:
                    This specification defines a protocol to enable a consumer
                    to obtain a web service's metadata, that is, its WSDL and
                    policies. It can be thought of as a bootstrap mechanism
                    for communication.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiav">
            <title>Message Optimization Specifications</title>

            <para>Message optimization is the process of transmitting web
            services messages in the most efficient manner. It is achieved in
            web services communication by encoding messages prior to
            transmission and then de-encoding them when they reach their final
            destination.</para>

            <para><xref linkend="ahiaw" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows the
            specifications that were implemented to optimize communication
            between two web service endpoints.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahiaw">
                <title>Message Optimization Specifications</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/MessageOptimizationStandards.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of message optimization
                        specifications</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In addition to the Core XML specifications, optimization was
            implemented using the following specifications:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>SOAP</emphasis>: With SOAP
                    implementations, client requests and web service responses
                    are most often transmitted as SOAP messages over HTTP to
                    enable a completely interoperable exchange between clients
                    and web services, all running on different platforms and
                    at various locations on the Internet. HTTP is a familiar
                    request-and response standard for sending messages over
                    the Internet, and SOAP is an XML-based protocol that
                    follows the HTTP request-and-response model. In SOAP 1.1,
                    the SOAP portion of a transported message handles the
                    following: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Defines an XML-based envelope to describe what
                                is in the message and how to process the
                                message.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Includes XML-based encoding rules to express
                                instances of application-defined data types within
                                the message.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Defines an XML-based convention for
                                representing the request to the remote service and
                                the resulting response.</para>

                                <para>In SOAP 1.2 implementations, web service
                                endpoint addresses can be included in the XML-based
                                SOAP envelope, rather than in the transport header
                                (for example in the HTTP transport header), thus
                                enabling SOAP messages to be transport
                                independent.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Addressing</emphasis>: This
                    specification defines a endpoint reference representation.
                    A web service endpoint is an entity, processor, or
                    resource that can be referenced and to which web services
                    messages can be addressed. Endpoint references convey the
                    information needed to address a web service endpoint. The
                    specification defines two constructs: message addressing
                    properties and endpoint references, that normalize the
                    information typically provided by transport protocols and
                    messaging systems in a way that is independent of any
                    particular transport or messaging system. This is
                    accomplished by defining XML tags for including web
                    service addresses in the SOAP message, instead of the HTTP
                    header. The implementation of these features enables
                    messaging systems to support message transmission in a
                    transport-neutral manner through networks that include
                    processing nodes such as endpoint managers, firewalls, and
                    gateways.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Secure
                    Conversation</emphasis>: This specification provides
                    better message-level security and efficiency in
                    multiple-message exchanges in a standardized way. It
                    defines basic mechanisms on top of which secure messaging
                    semantics can be defined for multiple-message exchanges
                    and allows for contexts to be established and potentially
                    more efficient keys or new key material to be exchanged,
                    thereby increasing the overall performance and security of
                    the subsequent exchanges.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>SOAP MTOM</emphasis>: The SOAP Message
                    Transmission Optimization Mechanism (MTOM), paired with
                    the XML-binary Optimized Packaging (XOP), provides
                    standard mechanisms for optimizing the transmission format
                    of SOAP messages by selectively encoding portions of the
                    SOAP message, while still presenting an XML Infoset to the
                    SOAP application. This mechanism enables the definition of
                    a hop-by-hop contract between a SOAP node and the next
                    SOAP node in the SOAP message path so as to facilitate the
                    efficient pass-through of optimized data contained within
                    headers or bodies of SOAP messages that are relayed by an
                    intermediary. Further, it enables message optimization to
                    be done in a binding independent way.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiax">
            <title>Reliable Messaging Specifications</title>

            <para>Reliability (in terms of WS-ReliableMessaging) is measured
            by a system's ability to deliver messages from point A to point B
            regardless of network errors. <xref linkend="ahiay"
            xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows the specifications that were
            implemented to ensure reliable delivery of messages between two
            web services endpoints.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahiay">
                <title>Reliable Messaging Specifications</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/reliableMessagingStandards.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of reliable messaging
                        specifications</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In addition to the Core XML specifications and supporting
            standards (Web Services Security and Web Services Policy, which
            are required building blocks), the reliability feature is
            implemented using the following specifications:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Reliable
                    Messaging</emphasis>: This specification defines a
                    standardized way to identify, track, and manage the
                    reliable delivery of messages between exactly two parties,
                    a source and a destination, so as to recover from failures
                    caused by messages being lost or received out of order.
                    The specification is also extensible so it allows
                    additional functionality, such as security, to be tightly
                    integrated. The implementation of this specification
                    integrates with and complements the Web Services Security,
                    and the Web Services Policy implementations.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Coordination</emphasis>: This
                    specification defines a framework for providing protocols
                    that coordinate the actions of distributed applications.
                    This framework is used by Web Services Atomic
                    Transactions. The implementation of this specification
                    enables the following capabilities: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Enables an application service to create the
                                context needed to propagate an activity to other
                                services and to register for coordination
                                protocols.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Enables existing transaction processing,
                                workflow, and other coordination systems to hide
                                their proprietary protocols and to operate in a
                                heterogeneous environment.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Defines the structure of context and the
                                requirements so that context can be propagated
                                between cooperating services.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Atomic
                    Transactions</emphasis>: This specification defines a
                    standardized way to support two-phase commit semantics
                    such that either all operations invoked within an atomic
                    transaction succeed or are all rolled back.
                    Implementations of this specification require the
                    implementation of the Web Services Coordination
                    specification.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahiaz">
            <title>Security Specifications</title>

            <para><xref linkend="ahiba" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows the
            specifications implemented to secure communication between two web
            service endpoints and across intermediate endpoints.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahiba">
                <title>Web Services Security Specifications</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/webServicesSecurityStandards.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of web services security
                        specifications</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In addition to the Core XML specifications, the security
            feature is implemented using the following specifications:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Security</emphasis>: This
                    specification defines a standard set of SOAP extensions
                    that can be used when building secure web services to
                    implement message content integrity and confidentiality.
                    The implementation provides message content integrity and
                    confidentiality even when communication traverses
                    intermediate nodes, thus overcoming a short coming of SSL.
                    The implementation can be used within a wide variety of
                    security models including PKI, Kerberos, and SSL and
                    provides support for multiple security token formats,
                    multiple trust domains, multiple signature formats, and
                    multiple encryption technologies.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Policy</emphasis>: This
                    specification provides a flexible and extensible grammar
                    for expressing the capabilities, requirements, and general
                    characteristics of a web service. It provides a framework
                    and a model for the expression of these properties as
                    policies and is a building block for Web Services Security
                    policy.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Trust</emphasis>: This
                    specification supports the following capabilities in a
                    standardized way: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Defines extensions to Web Services Security
                                that provide methods for issuing, renewing, and
                                validating security tokens used by Web services
                                security.</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                                <para>Establishes, assesses the presence of, and
                                brokers trust relationships.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Secure
                    Conversation</emphasis>: This specification defines a
                    standardized way to provide better message-level security
                    and efficiency in multiple-message exchanges. The Metro
                    implementation provides basic mechanisms on top of which
                    secure messaging semantics can be defined for
                    multiple-message exchanges and allows for contexts to be
                    established along with more efficient keys or new key
                    material. This approach increases the overall performance
                    and security of the subsequent exchanges. While the Web
                    Services Security specification, described above, focuses
                    on the message authentication model, it does leave
                    openings for several forms of attacks. The Secure
                    Conversation authentication specification defines a
                    standardized way to authenticate a series of messages,
                    thereby addressing the short comings of Web Services
                    Security. With the Web Services Security Conversation
                    model, the security context is defined as a new Web
                    Services security token type that is obtained using a
                    binding of Web Services Trust.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Web Services Security Policy</emphasis>:
                    This specification defines a standard set of patterns or
                    sets of assertions that represent common ways to describe
                    how messages are secured on a communications path. The
                    Metro implementation allows flexibility in terms of
                    tokens, cryptography, and mechanisms used, including
                    leveraging transport security, but is specific enough to
                    ensure interoperability based on assertion matching by web
                    service clients and web services providers.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ahibb">
        <title>How the Metro Technologies Work</title>

        <para>The following sections provide a high-level description of how
        the message optimization, reliable messaging, and security
        technologies work.</para>

        <section xml:id="ahibc">
            <title>How Message Optimization Works</title>

            <para>Message optimization ensures that web services messages are
            transmitted over the Internet in the most efficient manner.
            Because XML is a textual format, binary files must be represented
            using character sequences before they can be embedded in an XML
            document. A popular encoding that permits this embedding is known
            as base64 encoding, which corresponds to the XML Schema data type
            xsd:base64Binary. In a web services toolkit that supports a
            binding framework, a value of this type must be encoded before
            transmission and decoded before binding. The encoding and decoding
            process is expensive and the costs increase linearly as the size
            of the binary object increases.</para>

            <para>Message optimization enables web service endpoints to
            identify large binary message payloads, remove the message
            payloads from the body of the SOAP message, encode the message
            payloads using an efficient encoding mechanism (effectively
            reducing the size of the payloads), re-insert the message payloads
            into the SOAP message as attachments (the file is linked to the
            SOAP message body by means of an Include tag). Thus, message
            optimization is achieved by encoding binary objects prior to
            transmission and then de-encoding them when they reach there final
            destination.</para>

            <para>The optimization process is really quite simple. To effect
            optimized message transmissions, the sending endpoint checks the
            body of the SOAP message for XML encoded binary objects that
            exceed a predetermined size and encodes those objects for
            efficient transmission over the Internet.</para>

            <para>SOAP MTOM, paired with the XML-binary Optimized Packaging
            (XOP), addresses the inefficiencies related to the transmission of
            binary data in SOAP documents. Using MTOM and XOP, XML messages
            are dissected in order to transmit binary files as MIME
            attachments in a way that is transparent to the application. This
            transformation is restricted to base64 content in canonical form
            as defined in XSD Datatypes as specified in XML Schema Part 2:
            Datatypes Second Edition, W3C Recommendation 28 October
            2004.</para>

            <para>Thus, the Metro technology achieves message optimization
            through an implementation of the MTOM and XOP specifications. With
            the message optimization feature enabled, small binary objects are
            sent in-line in the SOAP body. For large binary objects, this
            becomes quite inefficient, so the binary object is separated from
            the SOAP body, encoded, sent as an attachment to the SOAP message,
            and decoded when it reaches its destination endpoint.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahibd">
            <title>How Reliable Messaging Works</title>

            <para>When reliable messaging is enabled, messages are grouped
            into sequences, which are defined by the client's proxies. Each
            proxy corresponds to a message sequence, which consists of all of
            the request messages for that proxy. Each message contains a
            sequence header. The header includes a sequence identifier that
            identifies the sequence and a unique message number that indicates
            the order of the message in the sequence. The web service endpoint
            uses the sequence header information to group the messages and, if
            the Ordered Delivery option is selected, to process them in the
            proper order. Additionally, if secure conversation is enabled,
            each message sequence is assigned its own security context token.
            The security context token is used to sign the handshake messages
            that initialize communication between two web service endpoints
            and subsequent application messages.</para>

            <para>Thus, using the Reliable Messaging technology, web service
            endpoints collaborate to determine which messages in a particular
            application message sequence arrived at the destination endpoint
            and which messages require resending. The reliable messaging
            protocol requires that the destination endpoint return
            message-receipt acknowledgements that include the sequence
            identifier and the message number of each message received. If the
            source determines that a message was not received by the
            destination, it resends the message and requests an
            acknowledgement. Once the source has sent all messages for a given
            sequence and their receipt has been acknowledged by the
            destination, the source terminates the sequence.</para>

            <para>The web service destination endpoint in turn sends the
            application messages along to the application. If ordered delivery
            is configured (optional), the destination endpoint reconstructs a
            complete stream of messages for each sequence in the exact order
            in which the messages were sent and sends them along to the
            destination application. Thus, through the use of the reliable
            messaging protocol, the destination endpoint is able to provide
            the following delivery assurances to the web service
            application:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Each message is delivered to the destination
                    application at least once.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Each message is delivered to the destination
                    application at most once.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Sequences of messages are grouped by sequence
                    identifiers and delivered to the destination application
                    in the order defined by the message numbers.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para><xref linkend="ahibe" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows a
            simplified view of client and web service application message
            exchanges when the Reliable Messaging protocol is not used.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahibe">
                <title>Application Message Exchange Without Reliable
                Messaging</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/appMessageExWORM.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of application message exchange
                        without reliable messaging</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>When the Reliable Messaging protocol is not used,
            application messages flow over the HTTP connection with no
            delivery assurances. If messages are lost in transit or delivered
            out of order, the communicating endpoints have no way of
            knowing.</para>

            <para><xref linkend="ahibf" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows a
            simplified view of client and web service application message
            exchanges when reliable messaging is enabled.</para>

            <figure xml:id="ahibf">
                <title>Application Message Exchange with Reliable Messaging
                Enabled</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/appMessageExWRM.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>

                    <textobject>
                        <simpara>Diagram of application message exchange with
                        reliable messaging enabled</simpara>
                    </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>With reliable messaging enabled, the Reliable Messaging
            source module is plugged into the Metro web service client. The
            source module transmits the application messages and keeps copies
            of the messages until their receipt is acknowledged by the
            destination module through the exchange of protocol messages. The
            destination module acknowledges messages and optionally buffers
            them for ordered-delivery guarantee. After guaranteeing order, if
            configured, the destination module allows the messages to proceed
            through the Metro dispatch for delivery to the endpoint or
            application destination.</para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="ahibg">
            <title>How Security Works</title>

            <para>The following sections describe how the Metro security
            technologies, security policy, trust, and secure conversation
            work.</para>

            <section xml:id="ahibh">
                <title>How Security Policy Works</title>

                <para>The Metro Web Service Security Policy implementation
                builds on the features provided by the Web Service Policy
                implementation in Metro. It enables users to use XML elements
                to specify the security requirements of a web service
                endpoint, that is, how messages are secured on the
                communication path between the client and the web service. The
                web service endpoint specifies the security requirements to
                the client as assertions (see <xref linkend="ahibi"
                xrefstyle="select:title" />).</para>

                <figure xml:id="ahibi">
                    <title>Security Policy Exchange</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                       fileref="figures/securityPolicyExchange.png"
                                       scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                        </imageobject>

                        <textobject>
                            <simpara>Diagram of security policy
                            exchange</simpara>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>The security policy model uses the policy specified in
                the WSDL file for associating policy assertions with web
                service communication. As a result, whenever possible, the
                security policy assertions do not use parameters or
                attributes. This enables first-level, <code>QName</code>-based
                assertion matching to be done at the framework level without
                security domain-specific knowledge. The first-level matching
                provides a narrowed set of policy alternatives that are shared
                by the client and web service endpoint when they attempt to
                establish a secure communication path.</para>

                <note>
                    <para>A <code>QName</code> is a qualified name, as
                    specified by the <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#QName">XML
                    Schema Part2: Datatypes specification</link>, <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names/#ns-qualnames">Namespaces
                    in XML</link>, and <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/XML/xml-names-19990114-errata">Namespaces
                    in XML Errata</link>. A qualified name is made up of a
                    namespace URI, a local part, and a prefix.</para>
                </note>

                <para>The benefit of representing security requirements as
                assertions is that <code>QName</code> matching is sufficient
                to find common security alternatives and that many aspects of
                security can be factored out and reused. For example, it may
                be common that the security mechanism is constant for a web
                service endpoint, but that the message parts that are
                protected, or secured, may vary by message action.</para>

                <para>The following types of assertions are supported:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Protection assertions</emphasis>:
                        Define the scope of security protection. These
                        assertions identify the message parts that are to be
                        protected and how they are to be protected, that is,
                        whether data integrity and confidentiality mechanisms
                        are to be used.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Conditional assertions</emphasis>:
                        Define general aspects or preconditions of the
                        security. These assertions define the relationships
                        within and the characteristics of the environment in
                        which security is being applied, such as the tokens
                        that can be used, which tokens are for integrity or
                        confidentiality protection, applicable algorithms to
                        use, and so on.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Security binding
                        assertions</emphasis>: Define the security mechanism
                        that is used to provide security. These assertions are
                        a logical grouping that defines how the conditional
                        assertions are used to protect the indicated message
                        parts. For example, the assertions might specify that
                        an asymmetric token is to be used with a digital
                        signature to provide integrity protection, and that
                        parts are to be encrypted with a symmetric key, which
                        is then encrypted using the public key of the
                        recipient. In their simplest form, the security
                        binding assertions restrict what can be placed in the
                        <code>wsse:Security</code> header and the associated
                        processing rules.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Supporting token
                        assertions</emphasis>: Define the token types and
                        usage patterns that can be used to secure individual
                        operations and/or parts of messages.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para><emphasis>Web Services Security and Trust
                        assertions</emphasis>: Define the token referencing
                        and trust options that can be used.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="ahibj">
                <title>How Trust Works</title>

                <para><xref linkend="ahibk" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows
                how the Web Services Trust technology establishes
                trust.</para>

                <figure xml:id="ahibk">
                    <title>Trust and Secure Conversation</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                       fileref="figures/trustSecureConversation.png"
                                       scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                        </imageobject>

                        <textobject>
                            <simpara>Diagram of trust and secure
                            conversation</simpara>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>To establish trust between a client, a Security Token
                Service, and a web service:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The client establishes an HTTPS connection with
                        the Secure Token Service using one of the following
                        methods: <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis>Username Authentication and
                                    Transport Security</emphasis>: The client
                                    authenticates to the Security Token Service using a
                                    username token. The Security Token Service uses a
                                    certificate to authenticate to the Client. Transport
                                    security is used for message protection.</para>
                                </listitem>

                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis>Mutual Authentication</emphasis>:
                                    Both the client-side and server-side use X509
                                    certificates to authenticate to each other. The
                                    client request is signed using Client's X509
                                    certificate, then signed using ephemeral key. The
                                    web service signs the response using keys derived
                                    from the client's key.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The client sends a RequestSecurityToken message
                        to the Security Token Service.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The Security Token Service sends a Security
                        Assertion Markup Language (SAML) token to the
                        Client.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The client uses the SAML token to authenticate
                        itself to the web service and trust is
                        established.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>All communication uses SOAP messages.</para>
            </section>

            <section xml:id="ahibl">
                <title>How Secure Conversation Works</title>

                <para><xref linkend="ahibm" xrefstyle="select:title" /> shows
                how the Web Services Secure Conversation technology
                establishes a secure conversation when the Trust technology is
                not used.</para>

                <figure xml:id="ahibm">
                    <title>Secure Conversation</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                       fileref="figures/secureConversation.png"
                                       scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                        </imageobject>

                        <textobject>
                            <simpara>Diagram of secure conversation</simpara>
                        </textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>To establish a secure conversation between a Client and
                a web service:</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The client sends a X509 Certificate to
                        authenticate itself to the web service.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The web service sends a X509 Certificate to
                        authenticate itself to the client.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>All communication uses SOAP messages.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
