<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

DO NOT ALTER OR REMOVE COPYRIGHT NOTICES OR THIS HEADER.

Copyright (c) 2010-2012 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

The contents of this file are subject to the terms of either the GNU
General Public License Version 2 only ("GPL") or the Common Development
and Distribution License("CDDL") (collectively, the "License").  You
may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  You can
obtain a copy of the License at
http://glassfish.java.net/public/CDDL+GPL_1_1.html
or packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.  See the License for the specific
language governing permissions and limitations under the License.

When distributing the software, include this License Header Notice in each
file and include the License file at packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.

GPL Classpath Exception:
Oracle designates this particular file as subject to the "Classpath"
exception as provided by Oracle in the GPL Version 2 section of the License
file that accompanied this code.

Modifications:
If applicable, add the following below the License Header, with the fields
enclosed by brackets [] replaced by your own identifying information:
"Portions Copyright [year] [name of copyright owner]"

Contributor(s):
If you wish your version of this file to be governed by only the CDDL or
only the GPL Version 2, indicate your decision by adding "[Contributor]
elects to include this software in this distribution under the [CDDL or GPL
Version 2] license."  If you don't indicate a single choice of license, a
recipient has the option to distribute your version of this file under
either the CDDL, the GPL Version 2 or to extend the choice of license to
its licensees as provided above.  However, if you add GPL Version 2 code
and therefore, elected the GPL Version 2 license, then the option applies
only if the new code is made subject to such option by the copyright
holder.

-->
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "metro.ent">
%ents;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="using_rm" xml:lang="en"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Using Reliable Messaging</title>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-config">
        <title>Introduction to Reliable Messaging</title>

        <para>In the SOAP messaging world, presence of software, system or
        network failures is a common issue web service developers need to deal
        with. This issue is even more obvious in mobile applications which
        access the corporate network through mobile-enabled channels with
        limited connectivity and connection quality, such as WiFi, UMTS or
        GPRS.</para>

        <para>WS-ReliableMessaging specification, an OASIS standard, addresses
        this issue by defining a modular mechanism for reliable transfer of
        messages. It defines a messaging protocol to identify, track, and
        manage the reliable transfer of messages between a source and a
        destination in an interoperable fashion. The modularity and the
        extension points defined in the mechanism allows integration of other
        quality of service features, such as message level security.</para>

        <para>Metro implementation of reliable messaging is based o
        WS-ReliableMessaging. As other Quality of Service features, Reliable
        Messaging is configured via WS-Policy expressions stored in the WSDL
        document of a web service or in the web service's WSIT configuration
        file. These XML-based expressions are designed for machine processing
        rather than for human readability. Metro comes with a tooling support
        in the form of a plug-in for <link
        xlink:href="http://www.netbeans.org">NetBeans IDE</link> which
        provides a convenient way to configure reliable messaging feature for
        your web services. It provides a dialog-based wizard that lets you
        fine-tune a few reliable messaging configuration properties. In
        general, the properties you configure on the web service endpoint
        apply to the web service client as well. On the other hand, the
        client-side configuration options have only local effect and let you
        tweak the client-specific behavior.</para>

        <para>In the following sections we will look at enabling reliable
        messaging with Metro in more detail. These sections also contain
        tables that describe configuration options in more detail for service
        endpoint (<xref linkend="using_rm-config_endpoint"
        xrefstyle="select:title" />) as well as service client (<xref
        linkend="client_rm_config_options" xrefstyle="select:title" />)
        side.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-config_endpoint">
        <title>Configuring Web Service Endpoint</title>

        <para>When creating a reliable web service, you first start by
        creating a web service using common steps described in section <xref
        linkend="using_metro-developing_with_nb" xrefstyle="select:title" />.
        Once the web service is created, a design view of the web service
        should open in the editor window. If the design view is not opened,
        locate your web service in the <guilabel>Projects</guilabel><emphasis
        role="bold"></emphasis> view and double-click the web service to open
        it in the editor window.</para>

        <para>In the design view, there is a <guilabel>Quality of
        Service</guilabel> section as show on the picture below: <figure
                xml:id="f0.21865766008323695">
                <title>Quality of Service (NetBeans)</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/nb6_5-qos-ws-design-view.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure> In this section you may either simply check the
        <guilabel>Reliable Message Delivery</guilabel> checkbox and accept the
        Reliable Messaging configuration defaults, which means that your RM
        configuration for your web service is done, or you may click the
        <guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> button to display the
        <guilabel>Quality of Service</guilabel> dialog as shown on the picture
        below. <figure xml:id="f0.19917454831806913">
                <title>Quality of Service - Advanced (NetBeans)</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/nb6_5-qos-dialog-main.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure> <note>
                <para>You may alternatively access the <guilabel>Quality of
                Service</guilabel> dialog by right clicking on a web service
                in the <guilabel>Projects</guilabel> view and selecting
                <guilabel>Edit Web Service Attributes</guilabel> from the
                context pop-up menu.</para>
            </note> The Quality of Service dialog contains more configuration
        options for Reliable Messaging. Some of these are accessible direclty
        while the most advance configuration details are hidden behind the
        <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> button in a seprate dialog presented on
        the next picture. <figure xml:id="f0.006706294753032083">
                <title>Advanced Reliable Messaging Attributes
                (NetBeans)</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                                   fileref="figures/nb6_5-qos-dialog-advanced-rm.png"
                                   scalefit="1" width="100%"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>

        <para>In order to provide better overview of the RM configuration
        options, we included the following table that povides a detailed
        description of all the reliable messaging configuration options
        available on the service endpoint.</para>

        <table xml:id="endpoint_rm_config_options">
            <title>Reliable Messaging Configuration Options for Service
            Endpoint</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <colspec />

                <colspec colwidth="2*" />

                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Option</entry>

                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Reliable Message Delivery</entry>

                        <entry>Enables or disables reliable messaging
                        feature.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Deliver Messages In Exact Order</entry>

                        <entry><para>Specifies whether the Reliable Messaging
                        protocol ensures that the application messages for a
                        given message sequence are delivered to the endpoint
                        application in the order indicated by the message
                        numbers.</para><para>This option increases the time to
                        process application message sequences and may result
                        in the degradation of web service performance.
                        Therefore, you should not enable this option unless
                        ordered delivery is required by the web
                        service.</para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Message Delivery Assurance</entry>

                        <entry>This option tells our Reliable Messaging
                        implementation what type of the message delivery
                        assurance is expected. Currently it can be set to
                        "Exactly Once" and "At Least Once". <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Exactly Once</emphasis>
                                    delivery assurance, as the name suggests, guarantees
                                    that each message request from the web service
                                    client will be delivered to the web service endpoint
                                    once and only once. By default, this delivery
                                    assurance strategy is applied.</para>
                                </listitem>

                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">At Least Once</emphasis>
                                    delivery assurance guarantees that each message
                                    request from the web service client will be
                                    delivered to the web service endpoint, however it is
                                    possible that duplicate messages may be delivered
                                    under some circumstances. In general, this type of
                                    delivery assurance may provide better
                                    performance.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Flow Control</entry>

                        <entry>Enables or disables the flow control feature.
                        When enabled, this feature works in conjunction with
                        the Max Buffer Size setting to determine the maximum
                        number of messages for sequence that can be stored at
                        the endpoint awaiting delivery to the application.
                        Messages may have to be withheld from the application
                        if ordered delivery is required and some of their
                        predecessors have not arrived. If the number of stored
                        messages reaches the threshold specified in the Max
                        Buffer Size setting, incoming messages belonging to
                        the sequence are ignored.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Maximum Flow Control Buffer Size</entry>

                        <entry>If Flow control is enabled, this value
                        specifies the number of request messages that will be
                        buffered in the RM session. The default setting is 32.
                        For more information, see the description of the Flow
                        Control option.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Inactivity Timeout</entry>

                        <entry><para>Specifies the time interval beyond which
                        either source or destination may terminate the RM
                        session due to inactivity. The default setting is
                        600,000 milliseconds (10 minutes). A web service
                        endpoint will always terminate session whose
                        inactivity timeout has expired.</para><para>This
                        option may be used to ensure the early removal of
                        stale RM sequences and thus reduce the memory
                        footprint of the service endpoint. Note that setting
                        the value of this option affects also the web service
                        proxy usage patterns in the client
                        applications.</para></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-config_client">
        <title>Configuring Web Service Client</title>

        <para>While most of the Reliable Messaging options are configured on
        the web service endpoint, there are some details that may be
        fine-tuned on the client side as well. To configure the client-side
        details of Reliable Messaging you first need to create a web service
        proxy. Section <xref
        linkend="wsit_example_with_nb-creating_wsit_client"
        xrefstyle="select:title" /> describes all the necessary steps.</para>

        <para>Once a web service proxy is created, you can find it in the
        <guilabel>Projects</guilabel> view under <guilabel>Web Service
        References</guilabel> item. By right-clicking on the we service proxy
        and selecting <guilabel>Edit Web Service Attributes</guilabel> from
        the opened context pop-up menu you may open a dialog that let's you
        specify additional RM details.</para>

        <para>When dialog opens, it may have multiple tabs. The Reliable
        messaging configuration options are located on the <guilabel>Quality
        of Service</guilabel> tab in <guilabel>Advanced
        Configuration</guilabel> section. Following table describes all the
        reliable messaging configuration options available on the web service
        client side.</para>

        <table xml:id="client_rm_config_options">
            <title>Reliable Messaging Configuration Options for Service
            Client</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <colspec />

                <colspec colwidth="2*" />

                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Option</entry>

                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>RM Resend Interval</entry>

                        <entry>The time in milliseconds after which the sender
                        (RMSource) attempts to redeliver unacknowledged
                        messages to the Reliable Messaging Destination
                        (RM-enabled WS endpoint). By default, resend happen
                        every 2000ms.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>RM Close Timeout</entry>

                        <entry>By default, the call to proxy.close() will not
                        return until all messages have been acknowledged. RM
                        close timeout is the interval (in milliseconds) that
                        the client runtime will block waiting for a call to
                        close() to return. If there are still unacknowledged
                        messages after this interval is reached, and the call
                        to close has returned, an error will be logged about
                        messages being lost.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>RM Ack Request Interval</entry>

                        <entry>The suggested minimum time that the sender
                        (RMSource) should allow to elapse between sending
                        consecutive Acknowledgement request messages to the
                        Reliable Messaging Destination (RM-enabled WS
                        endpoint).</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="advanced_rm_configuration">
        <title>Configurable features summary</title>

        <para>In the previous chapter we focused on configuring Metro reliable
        messaging using <link xlink:href="http://www.netbeans.org">NetBeans
        IDE</link>. This section is a summary of all Metro reliable messaging
        runtime features that can be configured since Metro v2.0 and higher.
        The summary lists all the features discussed before as well as all
        other features that can be only configured by manually editing the
        WSIT config file.</para>

        <para>Please note that this chapter focuses on features configurable
        with Metro v2.0 and higher.</para>

        <table xml:id="rm_assertion_namespaces">
            <title>Namespaces used within Metro Reliable Messaging WS-Policy
            Assertions</title>

            <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Prefix</entry>

                        <entry>Namespace</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>wsp</entry>

                        <entry>http://www.w3.org/ns/ws-policy</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>wsrmp10</entry>

                        <entry>http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/ws/2005/02/rm/policy</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>wsrmp</entry>

                        <entry>http://docs.oasis-open.org/ws-rx/wsrmp/200702</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>net30rmp</entry>

                        <entry>http://schemas.microsoft.com/net/2005/02/rm/policy</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>net35rmp</entry>

                        <entry>http://schemas.microsoft.com/ws-rx/wsrmp/200702</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>sunrmp</entry>

                        <entry>http://sun.com/2006/03/rm</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>sunrmcp</entry>

                        <entry>http://sun.com/2006/03/rm/client</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>metro</entry>

                        <entry>http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/metro/ws-rx/wsrmp/200702</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table xml:id="rm_feature_summary">
            <title>Reliable Messaging Configuration Features - Layout</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Feature
                        name</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis
                        role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">WS-RM 1.0 compatible
                        assertion</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">WS-RM 1.1+ compatible
                        assertion</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Enable Reliable Messaging + version</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Enable Reliable Messaging + version</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies that WS-ReliableMessaging protocol
                        MUST be used when sending messages. Defines also the
                        version of the WS-RM protocol to be used.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp10:RMAssertion</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Sequence Inactivity Timeout</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Sequence Inactivity Timeout</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies the time interval beyond which either
                        RM Source or RM Destination may terminate the RM
                        sequence due to inactivity. The default setting is
                        600,000 milliseconds (10 minutes). A web service
                        endpoint will always terminate session whose
                        inactivity timeout has expired. Specified in
                        milliseconds.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp10:RMAssertion/wsrmp10:InactivityTimeout</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net35rmp:InactivityTimeout</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Acknowledgement interval</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Acknowledgement interval</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies the duration after which the RM
                        Destination will transmit an acknowledgement. If
                        omitted, there is no implied value. Specified in
                        milliseconds.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp10:RMAssertion/wsrmp10:AcknowledgementInterval</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net35rmp:AcknowledgementInterval</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Retransmission Interval</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Retransmission Interval</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies how long the RM Source will wait
                        after transmitting a message and before retransmitting
                        the message. If omitted, there is no implied value.
                        Specified in milliseconds.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp10:RMAssertion/wsrmp10:BaseRetransmissionInterval</code><code>/sunrmcp:ResendInterval</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:RetransmissionConfig/metro:Interval</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Retransmission Interval Adjustment Algorithm</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Retransmission Interval Adjustment
                        Algorithm</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies that the retransmission interval will
                        be adjusted using a specific (e.g. exponential
                        back-off) algorithm.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para><code>/wsrmp10:RMAssertion/wsrmp10:ExponentialBackoff</code></para><para>("Exponential
                        backoff" algorithm only)</para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:RetransmissionConfig/metro:Algorithm</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Maximum Retransmission Count</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Maximum Retransmission Count</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para>A message is considered to be transferred
                        if its delivery at the recipient has been acknowledged
                        by the recipient.</para><para>If an acknowledgment has
                        not been received within a certain amount of time for
                        a message that has been transmitted, the
                        infrastructure automatically retransmits the message.
                        The infrastructure tries to send the message for at
                        most a preconfigured number of times. Not receiving an
                        acknowledgment before this limit is reached is
                        considered a fatal communication failure, and causes
                        the RM session to fail.</para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:RetransmissionConfig/metro:MaxRetries</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Close sequence timeout</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Close sequence timeout</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>By default, the call to proxy.close() will not
                        return until all messages have been acknowledged. RM
                        close timeout is the interval (in milliseconds) that
                        the client runtime will block waiting for a call to
                        close() to return. If there are still unacknowledged
                        messages after this interval is reached, and the call
                        to close has returned, an error will be logged about
                        messages being lost.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><para><code>/sunrmcp:CloseTimeout</code></para><para>(client
                        side only)</para></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:CloseSequenceTimeout</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Acknowledgement request interval</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Acknowledgement request interval</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Defines the suggested minimum time that the
                        sender (RM Source) should allow to elapse between
                        sending consecutive Acknowledgement request messages
                        to the RM Destination.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/sunrmcp:AckRequestInterval</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:AckRequestInterval</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Bind RM sequence to security token</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Bind RM sequence to security token</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Defines the requirement that an RM Sequence
                        MUST be bound to an explicit token that is referenced
                        from a wsse:SecurityTokenReference in the
                        CreateSequence message.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:SequenceSTR</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Bind RM sequence to secured transport</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Bind RM sequence to secured transport</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Defines the requirement that an RM Sequence
                        MUST be bound to the session(s) of the underlying
                        transport-level protocol used to carry the
                        CreateSequence and CreateSequenceResponse message.
                        (When present, this assertion MUST be used in
                        conjunction with the sp:TransportBinding
                        assertion.)</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:SequenceTransportSecurity</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Exactly once delivery</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Exactly once delivery</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Each message is to be delivered exactly once;
                        if a message cannot be delivered then an error MUST be
                        raised by the RM Source and/or RM Destination. The
                        requirement on an RM Source is that it SHOULD retry
                        transmission of every message sent by the Application
                        Source until it receives an acknowledgement from the
                        RM Destination. The requirement on the RM Destination
                        is that it SHOULD retry the transfer to the
                        Application Destination of any message that it accepts
                        from the RM Source until that message has been
                        successfully delivered, and that it MUST NOT deliver a
                        duplicate of a message that has already been
                        delivered.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>default</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:DeliveryAssurance/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:ExactlyOnce</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>At Most once delivery</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>At Most once delivery</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Each message is to be delivered at most once.
                        The RM Source MAY retry transmission of unacknowledged
                        messages, but is NOT REQUIRED to do so. The
                        requirement on the RM Destination is that it MUST
                        filter out duplicate messages, i.e. that it MUST NOT
                        deliver a duplicate of a message that has already been
                        delivered.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:DeliveryAssurance/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:AtMostOnce</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>At Least once delivery</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>At Least once delivery</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Each message is to be delivered at least once,
                        or else an error MUST be raised by the RM Source
                        and/or RM Destination. The requirement on an RM Source
                        is that it SHOULD retry transmission of every message
                        sent by the Application Source until it receives an
                        acknowledgement from the RM Destination. The
                        requirement on the RM Destination is that it SHOULD
                        retry the transfer to the Application Destination of
                        any message that it accepts from the RM Source, until
                        that message has been successfully delivered. There is
                        no requirement for the RM Destination to apply
                        duplicate message filtering.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/sunrmcp:AllowDuplicates</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:DeliveryAssurance/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:AtLeastOnce</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>InOrder delivery</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>InOrder delivery</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Messages from each individual Sequence are to
                        be delivered in the same order they have been sent by
                        the Application Source. The requirement on an RM
                        Source is that it MUST ensure that the ordinal
                        position of each message in the Sequence (as indicated
                        by a message Sequence number) is consistent with the
                        order in which the messages have been sent from the
                        Application Source. The requirement on the RM
                        Destination is that it MUST deliver received messages
                        for each Sequence in the order indicated by the
                        message numbering. This DeliveryAssurance can be used
                        in combination with any of the AtLeastOnce, AtMostOnce
                        or ExactlyOnce assertions, and the requirements of
                        those assertions MUST also be met. In particular if
                        the AtLeastOnce or ExactlyOnce assertion applies and
                        the RM Destination detects a gap in the Sequence then
                        the RM Destination MUST NOT deliver any subsequent
                        messages from that Sequence until the missing messages
                        are received or until the Sequence is closed.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/sunrmp:Ordered</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/wsrmp:RMAssertion/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:DeliveryAssurance/wsp:Policy/wsrmp:InOrder</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Flow Control</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Flow Control</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Enables or disables the flow control feature.
                        When enabled, this feature works in conjunction with
                        the Max Buffer Size setting to determine the maximum
                        number of messages for sequence that can be stored at
                        the endpoint awaiting delivery to the application.
                        Messages may have to be withheld from the application
                        if ordered delivery is required and some of their
                        predecessors have not arrived. If the number of stored
                        messages reaches the threshold specified in the Max
                        Buffer Size setting, incoming messages belonging to
                        the sequence are ignored.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net30rmp:RmFlowControl</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net30rmp:RmFlowControl</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Maximum Flow Control Buffer Size</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Maximum Flow Control Buffer Size</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>If Flow control is enabled, this value
                        specifies the number of request messages that will be
                        buffered in the RM session. The default setting is 32.
                        For more information, see the description of the Flow
                        Control option.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net30rmp:RmFlowControl/net30rmp:MaxReceiveBufferSize</code></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/net30rmp:RmFlowControl/net30rmp:MaxReceiveBufferSize</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Maximum concurrent RM sessions</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Maximum concurrent RM sessions</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies how many concurrently active RM
                        sessions (measured based on inbound RM sequences) the
                        SequenceManager dedicated to the WS Endpoint accepts
                        before starting to refuse new requests for sequence
                        creation.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:MaxConcurrentSessions</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Reliable Messaging Persistence</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Reliable Messaging Persistence</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies whether the runtime should use
                        persistent sequence and message storage or
                        not.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:Persistent</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
            <title>Sequence manager maintenace task execution period</title>

            <tgroup cols="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                <colspec align="center" />

                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Sequence manager maintenace task execution
                        period</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>Specifies the period (in milliseconds) of a
                        sequence maintenance task execution. Sequence
                        maintenance task takes care of terminating inactive
                        sequences and removing the terminated sequences from
                        the sequence repository.</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>N/A</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry><code>/metro:MaintenanceTaskPeriod</code></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-creating_ws_and_client">
        <title>Creating Web Service Providers and Clients that use Reliable
        Messaging</title>

        <para>Examples and detailed instructions on how to create web service
        providers and clients that use reliable messaging are provided in the
        following chapters: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For an example of creating a web service and a
                    client using a web container and NetBeans IDE, see <xref
                    linkend="using_metro-developing_with_nb"
                    xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>For an example of creating a web service and a
                    client using only a web container, see <xref
                    linkend="ahifl" xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-with_sc">
        <title>Using Secure Conversation With Reliable Messaging</title>

        <para>If Secure Conversation is enabled for the web service endpoint,
        the web service acquires a Security Context Token (SCT) for each
        application message sequence, that is, each message sequence is
        assigned a different SCT. The web service then uses that token to sign
        all messages exchanged for that message sequence between the source
        and destination for the life of the sequence. Hence, there are two
        benefits in using Secure Conversation with Reliable Messaging:
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The sequence messages are secure while in transit
                    between the source and destination endpoints.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>If there are different users accessing data at the
                    source and destination endpoints, the SCT prevents users
                    from seeing someone else's data. <note>
                            <para>Secure Conversation is a WS-Security option,
                            not a reliable messaging option. If Secure
                            Conversation is enabled on the web service endpoint,
                            Reliable Messaging uses Security Context
                            Tokens.</para>
                        </note></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist> For more information on how to use Secure
        Conversation, see <xref linkend="ahici"
        xrefstyle="select:title" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="using_rm-ha_support">
        <title>High Availability Support in Reliable Messaging</title>

        <para>Starting with the <link
        xlink:href="http://metro.java.net/2.1/">Metro 2.1 release</link> Metro
        implementation of reliable messaging supports deployment in clustered
        environment configurations of the <link
        xlink:href="http://glassfish.java.net">GlassFish</link> Application
        Server 3.1 and higher. The only untested and thus currently officially
        unsupported reliable messaging feature in an HA environment is
        in-order message delivery. For more details see <link
        xlink:href="http://wsit.java.net/status-notes/status-notes-2-1-FCS.html#rm">RM
        section of the WSIT 2.1 Release Notes</link>.</para>

        <para>For a general overview of Metro High Availability support,
        please consult <xref linkend="using_metro-ha_support"
        xrefstyle="select:title" /> section.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
